Hey guys, it's Benefits of Ge from GE
Tracker here.
And a disclaimer real quick for this
video is I'm not going to be showing
anything that I've personally done
during the market panic that has
recently just happened.
But rather as a merchant, you can kind
of protect yourself from events like
this in the future and try and profit
off of this if you're risky enough to do
so. Now, there's already been quite a
lot of posts on why the market crashed
and I'm not going to go into that in
this video.
Um but a popular YouTuber content
creator by the name of Seven also made a
post about this a couple of days ago.
And the most important thing I wanted
note off of this post is
this right here.
The only people who are really hurt by
this market shift are those that sell
their gear midway through the panic and
then have to overpay when prices rebound
and stabilize.
Now, the
um
If you've ever watched my video game
updates, I've gone through a wide
variety of updates that have happened in
the game, the market shift that happens
during them,
the community thought process during
that and then as a merchant, how you
could have thought during that time.
And uh
one of the one of the key factors that
I've mentioned in that video is that
anytime that there's a drop in price, if
it's if it's a hard enough drop, there's
always going to be rebound. And he he
even recognizes this and mentions that
there is going to be rebound.
Um this was like 2 days ago and normally
I don't like to talk about markets. I
don't like to talk about items
or the market if it's too close to
um kind of things changing, but I feel
comfortable now making a video on this
thing as though the community has kind
of calmed down a little bit. It's not as
chaotic as it used to be. But as as a
merchant, um
during these times of panic, they can
either be
a great time for you to make a lot of
money or if you're not careful, you can
lose a lot of money.
And I do have here at the very top, I
have three different items that I want
to go into
uh just as examples.
Please keep in mind, this is not
endorsing any specific item to flip.
This is looking at their past behavior
and looking at, you know, analyzing how
and why they behaved the certain way
they did. Uh you guys already know why
they crashed, but in terms of a
merchant's perspective, we're going to
look a little bit deeper into that.
And then again, um
I feel comfortable talking about these
now because of where the market is and
from this point forward, however, any
item behaves is entirely up to you as a
merchant how you flip it. So again, this
is not endorsing any of these items, but
I wanted to talk about these
specifically.
And so first one I have the arcane
spirit shield. Now, the arcane was
sitting at about 130 mil
before it started crashing.
Yeah, so like 130 mil before it started
crashing and then the update came
world map and balancing changes,
massive panic ensues and the whole
community just kind of goes into spiral.
The next one we have
is a dragon warhammer.
See, let's look at the monthly time
frame.
Okay, so this was initially, let's see.
So this was a little rocky um
in the past. So this was something that
was
teetering for a while, but with this
recent update, it also started to face a
little bit more of uncertainty and
started rocking a little bit harder than
it used to in the past. Um so those are
things to pay attention to.
And then then the last one
And then the last one we have here is my
favorite graph. So if we
kind of zoom out, we're on the yearly
time frame.
Okay, there we go.
So if we look at the yearly time frame,
we can see the amount traded graph
alongside the price graph.
And I mean, the first thing that you
should notice is that the amount traded
graph is just going kind of going up
in a steady line.
And for a while this item was trying to
stay at around uh
60-ish mil,
50-ish mil. And there have been a lot of
arguments as to why this item should
have been valued at where it's at.
But I think
I have to be very careful when I say
this. I have I think
people are overvaluing an item in which
this item is easily obtained
through a method that is
arguably the most poss arguably the most
popular thing to do in Old School
RuneScape. And because of that, I mean,
you can obviously see here that the
amount coming in is just steady steadily
rising. So
in terms of whatever you guys if you
guys are looking at this item, in terms
of whatever you guys think it's valued
for the future, that's entirely up to
you. But I I wanted to throw this graph
in here because I found it very
interesting with the recent price crash
when it came to world map balancing and
changes. I can't see this item ever
hitting 70 mil ever again in the future
and if it does, I'll be shocked. But it
is possible. Um another thing you want
to pay attention to when it comes to
updates updates like this is that you're
going to want to have each of those item
pages open. Now, if you're not a premium
user, I don't think this works for you,
but if you're a premium user, um
if you if you're a premium user, then
you're going to get these live price
updates that come in as uh the site as
the site touches them.
So you'll see the uh past transactions
and you'll see how kind of the trade
you're coming in.
And if we kind of go down here,
also as a premium member, you're going
to have the day time frame, which is a
little bit more accurate than everyone
else. But again, when a market crashes
as it quickly as quickly as it did
um during this time, I think it went
from like 110
all the way down to
It went It went below 80 mil.
I believe it went I believe it went a
little bit
lower than 80 mil. But if you were
watching the graph during this time
frame,
during this little
dip here,
then you would have um
this this site this the live price
updates wouldn't have been coming in as
quickly as, you know, what the price is
actually in game.
So in order to combat something like
that, you're going to want to pay
attention to the buying and selling
quantity section on the upper hand
portion of this. And normally with an
update like this, I'll constantly
refresh the page over and over again,
maybe every 10, 15 minutes to see how
it's changing, maybe even a little bit
sooner. Um
given how quickly a community panics. So
with the arcane spirit shield,
at any given moment, I might see
20 people selling it, whereas
five people are buying it. Another
moment, I'll see
15 people buying it and five selling it.
So and then those those turning points
are what you're going to want to pay
attention to as a merchant because as
these things kind of spiral down,
they're going to hit these little
rebounds and in between those rebounds
is where you can make money. But again,
like Seven said, if you're not careful,
if you're not experienced, you know,
selling your gear midway through the mid
through the fall is really dangerous and
you could lose a lot of money. So if
you're brand new player or brand new
merchant and you're
you're freaking out during this this
panic and you held onto your arcane um
when it hit 110 mil, you're like, "Okay,
you know what? It can't go any lower
than this. Perfectly fine." And then all
of a sudden it started going to 100 mil
and then 90 mil and you start freaking
out and then now all of a sudden it's 80
mil
and then you sell it for like 75 mil.
And then all of a sudden, you look at
the very top of this and you see now
there's more people buying it as opposed
to selling it, which would indicate a
positive buy-sell ratio. And then you're
going to start seeing the item start
going back up again. And on if you're a
premium user, you're going to see it
more quickly
than anyone else on the site by using
the day time frame.
But again, those things happen so quick
that the site can't even keep up. But in
terms of trying to combat that and
trying to keep yourself with those edges
or trying to keep yourself those edges
over time, you're going to want to pay
attention to the buying and selling
quantity and the buy-sell ratio at all
times during those panics.
I wanted to show you guys my favorite
items table
because I wanted to show you guys how
you might use it as a market indicator
to determine the overall health of
RuneScape. But at the same time, I'm not
going to show my entire favorites list
because I want to kind of go into this
more in depth with another video that I
have planned for you guys that's going
to talk about
these rises and
crashes more in depth and specifically
focus on that as a merchant and how you
could protect yourself during those
times or of course try to make money.
So keep in mind, the items that I'm
showing here, I'm not again trying to
endorse any of these specific items for
flipping. These are solely market
indicators that help me determine how
the market's moving overall.
So we can see with the twisted bow,
codeai one, elder maul, lion spirit
shield, arcane spirit shield and dragon
claws, these are some of the most
valuable PVM items in game and obviously
PVM is going to be high in demand. So
these items are going to be the highest
in demand, highest valued, and have the
most use.
So, if we keep these on our favorites
tool, we can see with the site, it's
going to kind of update this all the
time. It's going to show us the buy-sell
ratio, which is going to help us
determine whether or not where this is
moving.
But more importantly, I mean, if you
guys can see, all of this is just red.
The entire these all these items right
now are just red. So, it's indicating
that these have gone down in value, and
they they've lost
value recently. So, that's that's one
way to look at it, but at the same time,
um you can't you can never ever look at
these tables at face value, because if
we look at the Elysian spirit shield,
um
within the market panic, it was much
lower than 330 mil.
And it's recently picked up back to a
more stable price point, but it's still
labeled as red. So, again, you can't
take these at face value, but the
combination of all of these items
present being red
is a good indication that recently there
was a market crash, markets um that
items have lost their value, and so
that's something that you could you
could use to your advantage when
something like this happens. If you ever
log in to GE tracker, and you see your
favorites list looking all red,
that's that should be a red sign that
you should be acting right there and
then.
Especially when it comes to items like
this of high value.
So, yeah guys, really the moral of the
story is that
when stuff like this happens,
you have to be very attentive and keep
your emotions out of the game and make
smart choices. So, the first step is to
actually make sure that you're always
paying attention to Thursdays. Always
paying attention to Thursdays. So, if
you live in the US, those updates are
going to come in probably while you're
sleeping.
Um so, I'm
I'm normally, I'd say nine out of 10
times, I'm going to be up early on
Thursday mornings so I can see what
those updates are coming in
and kind of make my
um flips accordingly to that. Um and I
would advise if you guys live in the US
as well to do the same so you guys can
stay on tune with how the market shifts.
Cuz if you wait until
like maybe you came home from work that
day,
yeah, like I I can't
sometimes maybe your items would have
dropped by like 30% and you're going to
be too hesitant to sell your items. And
then now now because you're too hesitant
to sell your items, you're going to
continue to lose more money because you
didn't sell the items initially during
the shockwave that happened during that
morning. And another thing I didn't
mention in this video is always paying
attention to what everyone else is
saying. So,
during this time frame, I had to bite my
tongue a lot, but at the same time I was
also able to get a lot of input from
what other people were thinking. And
what other people are thinking are also
kind of a a factor in how the market
moves overall.
And I know I didn't go too much in depth
in this video, but I didn't for because
I and I but I didn't because I really
want to make another video about this
specifically on rises and falls and how
as a merchant you might behave during
those times, but this is definitely
going to give you a clear picture on
what that video is going to kind of
entail.
And uh I'm probably going to with that
video, I'm going to include more
examples, updates, and stuff like that,
and kind of go a little bit more
analytically into them. So, it might be
a a much longer video if if you're
interested in that.
But in terms of this video, again, the
lesson's really
make sure you act quickly, make sure you
act independently, make sure your
emotions are out of the game, make sure
you pay attention to what the mods are
doing, and make sure you always uh pay
attention to Thursdays. Thursdays are
going to be your most important day of
week,
um period. But other than that, guys, I
hope you guys like this video. And if
you did, be sure to leave a like down
below to show your support. Be sure to
subscribe for future content. Be sure to
leave a comment down below to give me
your thoughts. Good luck merch and guys,
and until next time.
[Music]